<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.1 20151215//EN" "https://jats.nlm.nih.gov/publishing/1.1/JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article" dtd-version="1.0" specific-use="sps-1.1" xml:lang="pt">
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">cint</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>Contexto Internacional</journal-title>
        <abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Contexto int.</abbrev-journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1982-0240</issn>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0102-8529</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro, Instituto de Relações Internacionais</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id" specific-use="scielo-v3">q4Gp5s7LWjHmPZYc5jDtZXG</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id" specific-use="scielo-v2">S0102-85292014000200385</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1590/S0102-85292014000200003</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Artigos</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>[Artigo Retratado] A Rodada Uruguai e a África: Uma Crítica à Abordagem Liberal do Regime de Comércio</article-title>
        <trans-title-group xml:lang="en">
          <trans-title>[Article Retraction] The Uruguay Round and Africa: A Critique of the Liberal Approach to the Trade Regime</trans-title>
        </trans-title-group>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Souza</surname>
            <given-names>Igor Abdalla Medina de</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff01">**</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="aff01">
          <label>**</label>
          <institution content-type="orgname">Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro</institution>
          <institution content-type="orgdiv1">Instituto de Relações Internacionais</institution>
          <institution content-type="orgdiv2"/>
          <email>igabdalla@yahoo.com.br</email>
          <institution content-type="original">Ph.D. em Ciências Políticas e Sociais pelo Instituto Universitário Europeu (Florença, Itália), diplomata de carreira e professor do Instituto de Relações Internacionais da Pontifícia Universidade Católica do Rio de Janeiro (IRI/PUC-Rio). E-mail: igabdalla@yahoo.com.br.</institution>
        </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <season>Jul-Dec</season>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>36</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>385</fpage>
      <lpage>416</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>16</day>
          <month>09</month>
          <year>2013</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>06</day>
          <month>06</month>
          <year>2014</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/">
          <license-p>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. </license-p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Desde o momento em que acadêmicos de Relações Internacionais enfocaram o GATT 1947 para convergir em torno do conceito de regimes, arranjos normativos têm sido concebidos como instrumentos que levam os Estados a melhoras de Pareto. Este artigo apresenta as estimativas de perdas absolutas da África com o Acordo da OMC para investigar a Rodada Uruguai do ponto de vista do conceito de poder institucional. Após resolverem amplas divergências em agricultura, os Estados Unidos e as Comunidades Europeias usaram o seu poder demercado paramudar o fórum da propriedade intelectual e impor aos países menos poderosos escolha entre aderir à OMC ou arcar com os custos de exclusão do novo regime de comércio. Desencadeou- se dinâmica de rolo compressor que aumentou os custos de exclusão e fez com que países africanos, que perdem em termos de PIB, renda real, exportações e medidas de bem-estar econômico, aderissem à organização. Aceitou-se a OMC como uma escolha pelo mal menor. A visão de soma positiva dos arranjos normativos cega acadêmicos de RI para a realidade de que instituições são frequentemente apresentadas como ofertas que os países mais pobres não podem recusar. As assimetrias criadas pelo Acordo da OMC seriam remediadas, na Rodada Doha, com abrangente liberalização agrícola, uma profunda revisão do TRIPS e suporte a que os países pobres possam arcar com custos de ajuste e implementação, bem como participar efetivamente das negociações de novos acordos e domecanismo de solução de controvérsias.</p>
      </abstract>
      <trans-abstract xml:lang="en">
        <p>From the time IR scholars focused on the GATT 1947 to converge around the concept of regimes in the 1980s, normative settings have been viewed as Pareto-improving devices. This article presents the estimates of absolute losses to Africa in order to investigate the Uruguay Round from the standpoint of institutional power. After having solved wide grievances in agriculture, the United States and the European Communities used their market power to shift the forum in charge of intellectual property and impose on weaker countries the choice between accepting the new organization and bearing the costs of exclusion. A bandwagon dynamic increased the costs of exclusion, leading African countries, which lose in terms of GDP, real income, exports and economic welfare, to accept the new trade regime. Accession to the WTO was thus the choice for the lesser evil. The liberal positive-sum view on institutions blinds IR scholars to the reality that institutions are frequently presented as offers poor countries cannot refuse. The asymmetries of the WTO Agreement would be remediated at the present Doha Round by agreements towards wide agricultural liberalization, a comprehensive reform of TRIPS and the provision of support for least developed countries to bear adjustment and implementation costs, as well as participate effectively at negotiations and the dispute settlement system.</p>
      </trans-abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="pt">
        <kwd>Liberalismo Internacionalista</kwd>
        <kwd>Regime do Comércio</kwd>
        <kwd>Organização Mundial do Comércio</kwd>
        <kwd>Rodada Uruguai</kwd>
        <kwd>Poder Institucional</kwd>
        <kwd>África</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <kwd>Liberal Internationalism</kwd>
        <kwd>Trade Regime</kwd>
        <kwd>World Trade Organization</kwd>
        <kwd>Uruguay Round</kwd>
        <kwd>Institutional Power</kwd>
        <kwd>Africa</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <counts>
        <fig-count count="2"/>
        <table-count count="4"/>
        <equation-count count="0"/>
        <ref-count count="57"/>
        <page-count count="32"/>
      </counts>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2014</year>
      </pub-date>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>The Editorial Committee of Contexto Internacional has decided, upon deliberation, to retract the following research article:</p>
    <p>Igor Abdallah Medina de Souza, The Uruguay Round and Africa: A Liberal Approach to the Trade Regime, Contexto Internacional, December 2014. http://dx.doi.org/10.1590/S0102-85292014000200003</p>
    <p>Since it is a close transcription (with the exception of some parts) of a previously published paper:</p>
    <p>Igor Abdallah Medina de Souza, "An offer developing countries could not refuse: how powerful states created the World Trade Organisation," Journal of International Relations and Development, 9 August 2013. doi:10.1057/jird.2013.18</p>
    <p>I would like to emphasise that the retraction process aims to correct and guarantee the integrity of academic communications and does not, in any way, represent a punishment to authors. Retraction is a fundamental mechanism to alert readers of problems related to already published manuscripts.</p>
    <p>Best regards,</p>
    <p>Carolina Moulin Chief Editor Contexto Internacional</p>
  </body>
</article>