<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd">
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" specific-use="sps-1.4" dtd-version="1.0" xml:lang="pt" article-type="research-article"><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">sur</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Sur. Revista Internacional de Direitos Humanos</journal-title><abbrev-journal-title abbrev-type="publisher">Sur, Rev. int. direitos human.</abbrev-journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="ppub">1806-6445</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1983-3342</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Sur - Rede Universitária de Direitos Humanos</publisher-name><publisher-loc>São Paulo, SP, Brazil</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id" specific-use="scielo-v2">S1806-64452005000100002</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id" specific-use="scielo-v1">S1806-6445(05)00200202</article-id><title-group><article-title>Os direitos humanos na implementação dos Objetivos de Desenvolvimento do Milênio</article-title><trans-title-group xml:lang="en"><trans-title>Reflections on human rights approaches to implementing the Millennium Development Goals</trans-title></trans-title-group><trans-title-group xml:lang="es"><trans-title>Los derechos humanos en la implementación de los Objetivos de Desarrollo del Milenio</trans-title></trans-title-group></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Azzam</surname><given-names>Fateh</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub-ppub"><year>2005</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>22</fpage><lpage>35</lpage><permissions><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/" xml:lang="en"><license-p>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial 4.0 International License.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>Este artigo discute a implementação dos Objetivos de Desenvolvimento do Milênio sob a perspectiva legal e de defesa dos direitos humanos, caracterizando o hiato existente entre as abordagens que focalizam os direitos humanos e as que se concentram mais nas necessidades de desenvolvimento. Apresenta uma nova interpretação do litígio de interesse público e da análise orçamentária, requerendo uma cooperação mais estreita entre os ativistas de direitos humanos e as organizações especializadas em desenvolvimento. Defende também a adoção de estratégias que articulem a participação da sociedade civil com as ações do governo, incluindo planos nacionais de ação voltados para aspectos específicos dos Objetivos do Milênio - por exemplo, a redução da pobreza -, nos quais se atribua um papel de liderança aos " conselhos nacionais" . Finalmente, faz um apelo para a inclusão dos refugiados e de outros migrantes forçados, populações que estão entre as mais marginalizadas e que, com freqüência, são excluídas dessas preocupações.</p></abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="en"><p>This article discusses the implementation of the Millennium Development Goals, characterizing the gap between human rights and development approaches. It offers a new interpretation for public interest law litigation and budget analysis, requiring closer cooperation between human rights lawyers and development organizations. It urges the adoption of a strategy that articulate a participatory collaboration between government and civil society organizations, including national plans geared to specific aspects of the Millennium Goals - e.g. reduction of poverty - in which a leading role is ascribed to "national councils". Finally, an appeal is made for the inclusion of refugees and other forced migrants as some of the most marginalized populations that are often excluded from these concerns.</p></trans-abstract><trans-abstract xml:lang="es"><p>Este artículo discute la implementación de los Objetivos de Desarrollo del Milenio desde la perspectiva legal y de defensa de los derechos humanos. Se caracteriza la brecha que existe entre los abordajes que apuntan a los derechos humanos y los que se concentran, fundamentalmente, en las necesidades de desarrollo. Presenta una nueva interpretación en lo que concierne al litigio de interés público y al análisis presupuestario, que requiere una cooperación más estrecha entre los activistas de derechos humanos y las organizaciones de desarrollo. Además, defiende la adopción de estrategias que articulen la participación de la sociedad civil en las acciones del gobierno, incluidos los planes nacionales dirigidos a aspectos específicos de los Objetivos del Milenio - por ejemplo, la reducción de la pobreza -, en los que se atribuya un papel de liderazgo a los " consejos nacionales" . Finalmente, hace un apelo para la inclusión de los refugiados y de otros migrantes forzados, sectores que se encuentran entre los más marginados y a quienes, frecuentemente, se los excluye de estas preocupaciones.</p></trans-abstract><counts><fig-count count="0"/><table-count count="0"/><equation-count count="0"/><ref-count count="13"/><page-count count="14"/></counts></article-meta></front><back><ref-list><ref id="B1"><element-citation publication-type="confproc"><date><year>2004</year><month>10</month><day>12</day></date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B2"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Millennium Development Goals: A compact among nations to end human poverty</source></element-citation></ref><ref id="B3"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Ripple in Still Water: Reflections by Activists on Local and National-Level Work on Economic, Social and Cultural Rights</source><date><year>1997</year></date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B4"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Circle of Rights</source><date><year>2000</year></date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B5"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>The Poverty of Rights: Human Rights and the Eradication of Poverty</source><date><year>2001</year></date><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Van Genugten</surname><given-names>Willem</given-names></name><name><surname>Perez-Bustillo</surname><given-names>Camilo</given-names></name></person-group></element-citation></ref><ref id="B6"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Many Roads to Justice: The Law Related Work of Ford Foundation Grantees around the World</source><date><year>2000</year></date><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McClymont</surname><given-names>Mary M.</given-names></name><name><surname>Golub</surname><given-names>Stephen</given-names></name></person-group></element-citation></ref><ref id="B7"><element-citation publication-type="journal"><article-title>Draft Articles on State Responsibility</article-title><source>Yearbook of the International Law Commission</source><date><year>1977</year></date><volume>11</volume><comment>Parte 1</comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="B8"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>A Rights-Based Approach to Budget Analysis</source><date><year>2000</year></date><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Diokno</surname><given-names>Maria Socorro</given-names></name></person-group></element-citation></ref><ref id="B9"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Education-Africa: Calls for Global Campaign to Abolish Primary School Fees</source><date><year>2000</year><month>12</month><day>06</day></date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B10"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Duties sans Frontières: Human Rights and Global Social Justice</source><date><year>2003</year></date><fpage>5</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B11"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Poverty Reduction Strategies</source><date><year>2002</year></date></element-citation></ref><ref id="B12"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Global Refugee Trends</source><date><year>2004</year><month>06</month></date><fpage>1</fpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="B13"><element-citation publication-type="book"><source>Framework for Durable Solutions for Refugees and Persons of Concern</source><date><year>2003</year><month>05</month></date><fpage>9</fpage></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>